<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sam. Ld. Bp. of Oxon, his celebrated Reasons for abrogating the Test, and notions of idolatry answered by Samuel Arch-Deacon of Canterbury.</title>
            <author>Phillips, John, 1631-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54776</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825340</idno>
  <idno type="VID">29720</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240875130</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2099A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204561</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825340</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99825340e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2175:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sam. Ld. Bp. of Oxon, his celebrated Reasons for abrogating the Test, and notions of idolatry answered by Samuel Arch-Deacon of Canterbury.</title>
                  <author>Phillips, John, 1631-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Samuel Arch-Deacon of Canterbury" = John Phillips.</note>
                  <note>A comparison of "Reasons for abrogating the test, imposed upon all members of Parliament anno 1678. Octob. 30" and "A discourse of ecclesiastical politie" both by Samuel Parker. Parker was Archdeacon of Canterbury in 1686 when he became Bishop of Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Parker, Samuel, 1640-1688. --  Reasons for abrogating the test, imposed upon all members of Parliament anno 1678. Octob. 30 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Parker, Samuel, 1640-1688. --  Discourse of ecclesiastical politie --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Test Act --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Religious satire, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29720:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sam. L<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. B<seg rend="sup">p</seg>. of Oxon.</hi> His Celebrated REASONS FOR ABROGATING THE TEST; And NOTIONS of IDOLATRY, ANSWERED By SAMUEL Arch-Deacon of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>It's better to Indulge Mens <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Debaucheries,</hi> than their <hi>Consciences.</hi>
               <bibl>Sam. Park. <hi>Eccles. Pol.</hi> Pag. <hi>54.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:29720:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29720:2"/>
            <p>THere is nothing hereby intended to impugn the <hi>Abrogation of the TEST:</hi> May His Majesty's Sacred Will and Pleasure be fulfill'd; and may the Rights of the <hi>English Peerage</hi> remain Inviolable. But there seems to have been an absolute Necessity, for the AUTHOR of the <hi>Reasons for Abrogating the TEST,</hi> to have Repeal'd his most bitter Invectives against the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> and his tempestuous Indignation against <hi>Dissenters</hi> in general; so diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically opposite to the Serene and Pious Desires and Resolutions of His Majesty, to make His Subjects happy, and unite them to Him, as well by Inclination, as Duty; and to have shew'd his Compliance to His Majesty in all His most Laudable and Generous Designs, before he had singl'd out that particular Point of the <hi>TEST,</hi> meerly to hook in a Plea for <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> and his own New modell'd Notions of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> But let Others, whom it may concern, dispute those <hi>Controversies:</hi> The present Question is, Whether his Lordship of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> have retracted his Discourses of <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity;</hi> or at least, those Passages in them, which run so apparently counter to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's <hi>Gracious Declaration for Liberty of Conscience?</hi> Otherwise he may seem to have calculated his <hi>Writings</hi> for the various <hi>Meridians</hi> of <hi>State;</hi> and his <hi>Arguments</hi> will not bear that Weight, which (tho the same, yet) coming from Another Person, they would have done.</p>
            <p>NOW, there cannot be a more certain <hi>Touchstone</hi> of Truth of the <hi>Bishop</hi>'s, or <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s (which you please, for they are both the same Person's) <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity,</hi> than the <hi>Declaration</hi> it self: Only, out of his Christian Charity, the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> has Peopled the <hi>Kingdom</hi> with such a dreadful <hi>Canaille,</hi> (all but those of the <hi>Church of England</hi>) that Astonishment it self might wonder well, were his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conscionable <hi>Epithetes</hi> to be allow'd, that so Gracious, so Indulgent, so Soft and Calm a <hi>Declaration,</hi> should come forth in Kindness to such a Rabble: For <hi>Those</hi> whom his Majesty calls <hi>His Good Subjects,</hi> the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> continually stigmatizes with the foul <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thets</hi> of <hi>Jugglers, Dissemblers, Wicked, Rebellious,
<note place="margin">Ecclesiast. Polit. <hi>pag.</hi> 241, 242, 273, 319, 187.</note> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, Sons of Strife and Singularity, and most notorious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</hi> And, upon this Supposition, as the Foundation of his <hi>Pile,</hi> that the Generality of the People of <hi>England</hi> are such, (for he excepts none but those of the <hi>Church of England</hi>) he rears the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity;</hi> wherein he had only this Misfortune,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29720:3"/>to be of a quite contrary Opinion to his Prince; and that his <hi>Drace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks</hi> were not Repeal'd, before the <hi>Declaration</hi> came forth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Declaration</hi> expresses His Majesty's <hi>Earnest Desire to Establish His Government on such a Foundation, as to make his Subjects happy, and unite Them to Him as well by Inclination as Duty; which He thinks can be done by no means so effectual, as by granting Them the Free Exercise of their Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Politicks</hi> are of another Strain: For, in his <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity,</hi> p. 12. he says; <hi>That the Aim of his</hi> Discourse <hi>is, by representing the palpable Inconsistency of</hi> Phanatick <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Principles, with the Welfare and Security of</hi> Government, <hi>to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken</hi> Authority <hi>to beware of its worst, and most dangerous Enemies, and force them to Modesty and Obedience by Severity of Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 52. of the same <hi>Preface: If Princes</hi> (says he) <hi>would but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, how liable Mankind are to abuse themselves with serious and conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Villanies, they would quickly see it to be absolutely necessary to the Peace and Happiness of their</hi> Kingdoms, <hi>that there be set up a more severe</hi> Government <hi>over Men's</hi> Consciences, <hi>than over their</hi> Vices <hi>and</hi> Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 54. of the same, He boasts his having prov'd, <hi>That</hi> Indulgence <hi>and</hi> Toleration <hi>is the most Absolute sort of</hi> Anarchy; <hi>and that</hi> Princes <hi>may with less Hazard give</hi> Liberty <hi>to Men's</hi> Vices <hi>and</hi> Debaucheries, <hi>than to their</hi> Consciences.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Declaration</hi> is quite of another Temper: <hi>We humbly thank Almighty</hi> God, <hi>it is, and hath of a long Time been, Our constant Sense and Opinion, which upon divers Occasions We have declared, That</hi> Conscience <hi>ought not to be constrain'd, nor</hi> People <hi>forc'd in Matters of meer</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>But this will not be admitted by the <hi>Arch-Deacon: For,</hi> (says he, <hi>Ecclesiast. Pol.</hi> pag. 321.) <hi>When Men's</hi> Consciences <hi>are so squeamish, that they will rise against the</hi> Customs <hi>and</hi> Injunctions <hi>of the</hi> Church, <hi>She must scourge them into</hi> Order, <hi>and chastize them for their troublesome Peevishness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 324. <hi>(Eccles. Polit.)</hi> He pretends to have prov'd the <hi>Ʋna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable danger of</hi> Toleration, <hi>and keeping Religious Differences; That</hi> Religion <hi>must be govern'd by the same</hi> Rules, <hi>as all other Transactions of</hi> Human Life; and, <hi>That nothing can do it, but severe</hi> Laws; <hi>nor they neither, unless severely Executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecclesiast. Pol.</hi> pag. 311. <hi>If Princes</hi> (says he) <hi>will suffer themselves to be check'd in their</hi> Laws Spiritual <hi>by every</hi> Systematical Theologue, <hi>they may as well bear to see Themselves affronted in their</hi> Laws Civil <hi>by every</hi> Village-Attorney.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29720:3"/>
            <p> Pag. 284. <hi>But to Indulge</hi> Ideots <hi>in their Folly, because they threaten</hi> Authority <hi>to be Peevish and Scrupulous, and to Infest the</hi> Government <hi>with a sullen, and cross-grain'd</hi> Godliness, <hi>(an Artifice not much unlike the Tricks of froward Children) is, to suffer</hi> Ignorance <hi>to ride in Triumph; and therefore such Humorsom</hi> Saints <hi>must be lash'd out of their Sullenness, into</hi> Compliance, <hi>and better</hi> Manners. This (as the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> calls it, <hi>Preface</hi> to <hi>Bramhal's Vindication</hi>) was one of his <hi>Rhapsodies of hasty and huddled Thoughts.</hi> Most Divine Words, and most Seraphick Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity! But the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> will have <hi>Tenderness of Conscience</hi> to be <hi>Pride, Vanity,</hi> and <hi>Insolence,</hi> though all the <hi>Seven Champions</hi> should Contradict him.</p>
            <p>Pag. 273. <hi>He that pretends</hi> Conscience <hi>to vouch his</hi> Humor, <hi>and his</hi> Insolence, <hi>is a</hi> Villain, <hi>and an</hi> Hypocrite; <hi>and so far from deserving</hi> Pity, <hi>especially from</hi> Authority, <hi>that no</hi> Offenders <hi>can more need or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke their Severity.</hi> This may be True: But, where the Supream Government,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles. Pol. p.</hi> 27, 28, 35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which must of necessity be Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, Uuncontroulable, and Unlimited, as well in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more Sagaciously discerns beyond the <hi>Arch-Deacon's,</hi> that same <hi>Conscience</hi> to be neither <hi>Humors</hi> nor <hi>Insolence,</hi> nor will comprehend it under that Notion; there, it is to be hoped, the Man is not a <hi>Villain,</hi> nor an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> and so not liable to the Fury of Correction.</p>
            <p>Pag. 271. <hi>And therefore, if</hi> Princes <hi>will be Resolute, they may easily make the most Stubborn</hi> Consciences <hi>bend to their</hi> Commands; <hi>But, if they will not, they must submit Themselves, and their Power, to all the Follies and Passions of their Subjects.</hi> Probatum est. <hi>S.P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 270. <hi>Governours must look to the Publick, and let</hi> Tender Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences <hi>look to Themselves.</hi> Laws <hi>must be of an unyeilding, and unflexible Temper, and not soft and easie Things.</hi> Princes <hi>must not be diffident in their Maxims of</hi> Policy; <hi>but, as they must set up some to Themselves; so they must Act roundly up to them.</hi> Dii te donent Tonfore.—<hi>Quaere,</hi> Why this Counsel was not taken, since the Consel was given so long before the <hi>Declaration</hi> came forth?
<note place="margin">Declar. P. 2.</note>
               <hi>Answ. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was ever contrary to His Majesty's Inclination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 269. <hi>'Tis all one to the Concernments of Government, whether Tenderness of</hi> Conscience <hi>be Serious or Counterfeit: For whether so or so, 'tis directly contrary to the Ends and Interests of Government.</hi> Better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, than not Believed.</p>
            <p>Pag. 263. <hi>And what can be more destructive to all manner of</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>than to make all the Rules of</hi> Order <hi>and</hi> Discipline <hi>less Sacred, than the Whimsies of every</hi> Phanatick <hi>Zealot?</hi> Pray be patient, <hi>Sir,</hi> there's no such thing done.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29720:4"/>
            <p> Ibid. <hi>When to pick Quarrels with the</hi> Laws, <hi>and make Scruple of Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, shall be made the Specifick Character of the</hi> Godly: <hi>When giddy and humorous</hi> Zeal <hi>shall not only excuse, but hallow Disobedience; when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that has Fancy enough to fancy himself a Child of</hi> God, <hi>shall have License to despise Authority.</hi> Who would have been at the trouble of all this Rhetorick, had he known what would have followed?</p>
            <p>Pag. 253. <hi>In brief, The only Cause of all our Troubles and Disurbances, is, the Inflexible Perverseness of about an hundred Proud, Ignorant, and Seditious</hi> Preachers; <hi>against whom, if the Severity of the</hi> Laws <hi>were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly levell'd, how easie would it be to reduce the</hi> People <hi>to a Peaceable Temper?</hi> There were just Three more than his Number, and that spoil'd the Project.</p>
            <p>Pag. 187. <hi>What can be more apparently vain, than to talk of</hi> Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations, <hi>or to hope for any Possibility of</hi> Quiet <hi>or</hi> Settlement, <hi>till</hi> Authority <hi>shall see it necessary to scourge them into better</hi> Manners, <hi>and wiser</hi> Opinions?</p>
            <p>Pag. 219. <hi>'Tis easily possible for well-meaning People, through</hi> Ignorance <hi>or</hi> Inadvertency, <hi>to be betray'd into such unhappy</hi> Errors, <hi>as may tend to the</hi> Publick Disturbance; <hi>which, though it be not so much their</hi> Crime, <hi>as</hi> Infelicity; <hi>yes is there no Remedy, but it must expose them to the</hi> Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>of the</hi> Publick Rods <hi>and</hi> Axes. Surely, <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi>'s own Chaplain could not have preached more severe Divinity?</p>
            <p>Pag. 271. <hi>In brief, There is nothing so ungovernable, as a</hi> Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; <hi>or so restiff and inflexible, as</hi> Folly <hi>or</hi> Wickedness, <hi>when hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with</hi> Religion: <hi>And therefore, instead of being Comply'd with, they must be Restrain'd with a more peremptory and unyielding</hi> Rigor, <hi>than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and unsanctify'd</hi> Villany.</p>
            <p>Pag. 223. <hi>Nay, so easy it is for Men to deserve to be Punish'd for their</hi> Consciences, <hi>that there is no</hi> Nation <hi>in the</hi> World (<hi>were</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>rightly understood, and duly manag'd</hi>) <hi>wherein</hi> Mistakes <hi>and</hi> Abuses <hi>in</hi> Religion, <hi>would not supply the</hi> Galleys <hi>with vastly greater Numbers, than</hi> Villany. 'Tis a Comfort, Curst Cows have now short Horns.</p>
            <p>However, to this the Tender <hi>Declaration</hi> makes a Reply, declaring one of the Reasons of his Majesty's <hi>Indulgence</hi> to be, Because He finds, That <hi>Force in Matters of meer Religion,</hi> tends to the <hi>Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other side, the <hi>Arch-Deacon,</hi> in Opposition to the <hi>KING</hi>'s Reason, is for <hi>Depopulating the Land,</hi> and <hi>Peopling the Galleys;</hi> and arraigns that Government for want of Understanding, and due Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, that does not observe his Method of Cruelty. He is for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29720:4"/>
               <hi>Fillories, Whipping-Posts, Rods, Axes, Scourges,</hi> &amp;c. as if no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pleas'd him, but that described by <hi>Virgil</hi> in Hell:
<q>
                  <l>Hinc exaudiri gemitus, &amp; saeva sonare</l>
                  <l>Verbera; tum stridor Ferri, tractaeque catena.</l>
                  <l>— Accincta flagella</l>
                  <l>Tisiphone quatit insultans, torvosque sinistra</l>
                  <l>Intentans Angues vocat Agmina sava sororum.</l>
               </q> This, in the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Ecclesiastical Policy;</hi> and to shew, that no other <hi>Government</hi> will content him but this, <hi>Pag.</hi> 18. <hi>I leave it,</hi> (says he) <hi>to</hi> Governors <hi>themselves to judge, whether it does not concern them, with as much</hi> Vigilance <hi>and</hi> Severity, <hi>either to prevent the</hi> Rise, <hi>or suppress the</hi> Growth, (of <hi>Phanaticks</hi> he means, that find themselves aggrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the <hi>Penal Laws</hi>) <hi>as to punish any the foulest Crimes of</hi> Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality? <hi>And if they would but seriously consider into what</hi> Exorbitances <hi>peevish and untoward Principles about</hi> Religion <hi>improve themselves, they could not but perceive to be as much their Concernment to punish them with the severest</hi> Inflictions, <hi>as any whatsoever</hi> Principles <hi>and</hi> Rebellions <hi>in the</hi> State.—Well! The Business is consider'd, and his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity</hi> is found to be Deficient.</p>
            <p>Nay, he goes farther, and arraigns all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> for their Folly, under the Title of <hi>Governors:</hi> For, says he, in the following <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. <hi>This certainly has ever been one of the Fatal Miscarriages of all</hi> Governors, <hi>in that they have not been aware of this Fierce and Implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Enemy, (meaning the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> who care no more for <hi>Whips</hi> and <hi>Scourges,</hi> than the <hi>Devil</hi> does for <hi>Holy-Water</hi>) <hi>but have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to govern unruly</hi> Consciences <hi>by more easy and remiss</hi> Laws, <hi>than those that are only able to suppress scandalous and confess'd</hi> Villanies; <hi>and have thought them sufficiently Restrain'd, by threatning</hi> Punishments, <hi>without inflicting them. And indeed, in most</hi> Kingdoms, <hi>so little have</hi> Princes <hi>understood their own Interests in Matters of</hi> Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hearken, O ye <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and go to School again to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Discourses</hi> of <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, here is another bold touch: Prohibition <hi>disobliges</hi> Dissenters, <hi>and that is one Evil;</hi> Impunity <hi>allows them</hi> Toleration, <hi>but that is a Greater; and where</hi> Governors <hi>permit what their</hi> Laws <hi>permit,</hi> (This is not the present Case) <hi>there the</hi> Common-wealth <hi>must at once feel all the Evils both of</hi> Restraint <hi>and</hi> Liberty. <hi>So that, as they would expect</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Settlement, <hi>they must be sure, at first, to bind on their</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Laws <hi>with the streightest Knot; and afterwards keep them in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29720:5"/>Force and Countenance, by the Severity of the</hi> Law. <hi>Their</hi> Restraint <hi>must be proportion'd to the Ʋnruliness of their</hi> Conscience: <hi>and they must be manag'd with so much the greater Strictness, than all other Principles of</hi> Disturbance, <hi>by how much they are the more dangerous. Gratias Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine!</hi> now Princes understand what they have to do.</p>
            <p>Yet a little more of the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity.</hi> Beloved, in his <hi>Preface</hi> to Bishop <hi>Bramhal</hi>'s <hi>Vindication</hi> (for it is not Pag'd) you shall find it thus written: <hi>They</hi> (meaning the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> or Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants against the <hi>Penal Statutes</hi>) <hi>have been so long accustom'd to undutiful</hi> Demeanor, <hi>that it is to be fear'd, they are grown too Headstrong and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, to be aw'd into a more modest</hi> Behaviour <hi>by Threatnings of Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Therefore, <hi>it will be thought necessary to bridle their ungovern'd</hi> Tongues <hi>and</hi> Spirits <hi>with</hi> Pillories <hi>and</hi> Whipping-Posts.</p>
            <p>And at the Bottom of the same Page: <hi>To this Peevishness of their</hi> Humors, <hi>I might add the Restlesness of their</hi> Minds, <hi>that is always dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with the settled Frame of Things,</hi> (<hi>innuendo,</hi> the setled Penal Laws;) <hi>and that no Alterations can satisfy. If you condescend to their first</hi> Demands, <hi>you only encourage them to be making</hi> New Remonstran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Appease all their Old</hi> Complaints, <hi>and they are immediately picking New</hi> Faults <hi>to be Redress'd. They that at first only request</hi> Indulgence, <hi>will, when strong enough, demand it.</hi> In short, Give the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> an Inch, and they'll take an Ell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> (in the same <hi>Preface</hi>) <hi>should it ever so happen hereafter, that any</hi> King <hi>of</hi> England <hi>should be prevail'd with to deliver up the</hi> Church, (That is to say, to dispence with the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>TEST;</hi> for the <hi>TEST,</hi> notwithstanding the Reasons against it, must be included in this long <hi>Parenthesis,</hi> because the <hi>Church</hi> fram'd it) <hi>he had as good, at the same Time, resign up his</hi> Crown. And thus you see the Danger of the Present Government, through the <hi>Non-conformity</hi> to the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another Reason, why His Majesty was gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleas'd to <hi>Think, Force in Matters of meer Religion</hi> directly contrary to the Interest of Government; and that is, <hi>Spoyling of TRADE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Trade! cries the <hi>Arch-Deacon:</hi> Trade! No. Let Grass grow about the <hi>Custom-House,</hi> rather than abate one Tittle of my <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Polity: For,</hi> (in his <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Ecclesiast. Pol.</hi> Pag. 49.) <hi>'Tis notorious,</hi> (says he) <hi>that there is not any sort of</hi> People <hi>so inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to</hi> Seditious Practices, <hi>as the</hi> Trading Part <hi>of a</hi> Nation; <hi>and their</hi> Pride <hi>and</hi> Arrogance <hi>naturally increases with the</hi> Improvement <hi>of their</hi> Stock. <hi>And if we reflect upon our late miserable</hi> Distractions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29720:5"/>
               <hi>tis easy to observe, how the</hi> Quarrel <hi>was hatcht in</hi> Trade-<hi>Mens</hi> Shops, <hi>and cherisht by the Zeal of</hi> Prentices: (By the way this is plausible Nonsense all over.) But he goes on, Pag. 50. <hi>'Tis a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry odd and preposterous Piece of</hi> Policy, <hi>to design the enriching this sort of</hi> People, <hi>while their Heads are distempered with</hi> Religious Lunacies. And, Pag. 51. <hi>He is a very silly Man, and understands nothing of the</hi> Follies, Passions <hi>and</hi> Inclinations <hi>of</hi> Human Nature, <hi>who sees not there is no Creature so ungovernable, as a</hi> Wealthy Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick. And therefore, (Pag. 48.) <hi>I confess, I cannot but smile, when I observe how some, that would be thought wonderful grave and solemn</hi> Statesmen, <hi>labour with mighty Projects of setting up this and that</hi> Manufacture, <hi>in their several respective</hi> Towns <hi>and</hi> Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; <hi>and how eagerly they pursue these Petty</hi> Attemps, <hi>beyond the Great</hi> Affairs <hi>of a more Publick</hi> Concernment, (Meaning the dreadful and terrible Execution of the <hi>Penal Laws;</hi>) <hi>and how wisely they neglect the</hi> Settlement <hi>of a whole</hi> Nation, <hi>for the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of a</hi> Village <hi>or</hi> Burrough? Very pleasant <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity!</hi> No Man must eat or drink, or maintain his Family: The grand Relation of Human Necessities, depending one upon another, must stand still, to oblige the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Ecclesiastical Policy.</hi> Here's a <hi>Quietus est</hi> for above the Third Part of the Nation. None but those that can swallow a <hi>Surplice,</hi> and adore the <hi>Parochial Levite,</hi> must weave Camlets at <hi>Norwich,</hi> make Bays at <hi>Colchester,</hi> Spurs at <hi>Rippon,</hi> Nalls at <hi>Brommigeham,</hi> or Saddles at <hi>Burford.</hi> For why? <hi>There is not any sort of People so Seditious, as the Trading Part of the Nation.</hi> So that, supposing the greater Part of the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Part of the Nation</hi> be, as the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> calls them, <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks,</hi> and <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> (that is, Men conscientiously scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puling the Ceremonies of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) they must either be <hi>Scourg'd into better Manners</hi> with <hi>Bryars and Thorns;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to <hi>Bramhalls Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> or else the Nation must be laid waste and desolate. For, to tell you true, as good have no People, as those that will not pay Tithes; 'tis no matter for the KING's Duties, nor how the Nation may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise weaken'd and expos'd.</p>
            <p>There is yet behind one more Reason urg'd in the <hi>Declaration,</hi> and that is this; <hi>That force in matters of meer</hi> Religion, <hi>never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the end for which it was imploy'd;</hi> wherein His Majesty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares Himself the <hi>more confirm'd, by the Reflections he had made upon the Conduct of the four last Reigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, here's the utter Subversion of the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Policy,</hi> All meer Labour in vain; abundance of Ranting,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29720:6"/>Raving, Reviling Expressions; insomuch, that the <hi>Arch-Angel</hi> was more civil to the <hi>Devil,</hi> than the <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> to the <hi>Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> and yet all to no purpose. He has been at a great deal of pains in setting up <hi>Pillories</hi> and <hi>Whipping Posts</hi> in all Parts and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Kingdom; and now he may e'ne go, and pull 'em down again. What are now become of all his Politick <hi>Let but's?</hi> In his Preface to Bishop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s Vindication; <hi>Let but the</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>think it seasonable at any time to Reprieve them</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Dissenters</hi>) <hi>from the severity of the</hi> Laws, <hi>and they immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately start up into that Confidence, as to imagine themselves the only Darlings of</hi> State. <hi>Let but the</hi> Publick Rods <hi>be removed from their Backs, and they are presently full of Expectations to have them put into their own hands. If they are not always Scourg'd and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis'd, they will grow Sawcy, and must by all means become Cronies to</hi> Kings <hi>and</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>Many other Passages might have been Collected out of his several Bitter (if they may not be said to be Scurrilous) Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives against the <hi>Dissenters;</hi> but here are sufficient to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently Manifest, that the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity,</hi> was as great a <hi>Dissenter</hi> from the mild and tender Maxims of his Majesty's Government, and his constant Sense and Opinion, of a long time professed and declared upon several Occasions in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, as the <hi>Dissenters</hi> were dissatisfied with the Rigid Severity of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> or, at least, with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which makes it seem questionable, whether a Person, who has brandish'd his Pen with that Virulency against the <hi>Dissenters</hi> in general, and His Majesties Royal Opinion, and the Mature Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults of his most serious Deliberations, may be a proper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion against the <hi>Test?</hi> For most certainly, there has been much more said already, and much more to the purpose, than he has produced.</p>
            <p>On the other side,
<note place="margin">Preface to Bishop <hi>Bramhall's Vindicat.</hi>
               </note> he has most Dogmatically avouch'd, <hi>That if ever the Boisterous and unreasonable Opposition</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>of the</hi> Nonconformists <hi>to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>be Re-erected, it must be upon its</hi> Ruins: <hi>And that if ever the</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>get any Ground, or Advantage of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>they will be bound to make their acknowledgments to the</hi> Puritans, <hi>and the strength of their Assistance.</hi> Whence he draws his Conclusion, <hi>That it would be a pleasant Spectacle,</hi> (that is to say, A ridiculous oversight in Government) <hi>to see either the Classical or Congregational Discipline establish'd by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29720:6"/>
            <p> Moreover, in the 721. <hi>Pag.</hi> of the Vindication of his <hi>Eccles-Pol.</hi> He appeals to all Men, whether <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> be any better, than a License for <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confusion?</hi> Pag. 238. He says, <hi>That to grant Subjects a lawless and uncontroul'd</hi> Liberty of Conscience, <hi>in all Matters and Pretences of Religion, is to dissolve one half of the Government into perfect</hi> Anarchy, <hi>and yield up the Constitution of all Publick Affairs, to the Humor of every wild</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thusiast. And <hi>Pag.</hi> 553. you find it thus written; <hi>So that seeing an Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction</hi> (<hi>of</hi> Pillories <hi>and</hi> Whipping Posts, Thorns <hi>and</hi> Bryars) <hi>is ahsolutely necessary to prevent all Confusions arising from unrestrain'd</hi> Liberty, <hi>it is better that Mankind should be sometimes exposed to the Miseries of</hi> Tyranny <hi>and</hi> Persecution, <hi>than always Groan under the Intolerable Disorders of</hi> Anarchy, <hi>or Reluctancy to</hi> Penal Statutes.</p>
            <p>If then the Church of <hi>England</hi> be Establish'd upon such a firm Foundation, that nothing can endanger it; but Indulgence to the <hi>Dissenters,</hi> 'tis to be admir'd, that a Man, so knowing in <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Policy,</hi> and so great a Friend to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> would open such a Gap as to plead for the <hi>Abrogation</hi> of the <hi>Test,</hi> which the Church-Men of <hi>England</hi> fram'd and set up, as the only <hi>Bulwark</hi> to prevent her Dissolution. So that, to use his own Words, <hi>'Tis very hardly Credible, That a Person, who has lately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd so vigorously in her Cause, should, notwithstanding all his seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Zeal and Earnestness, be really in good earnest, in his Pretences, against the</hi> Test. For, what signifies the Abrogating the <hi>Test,</hi> if there be no way to shake the otherwise immovable Church of <hi>England,</hi> but by making two Bridges of <hi>Dissenters,</hi> one between <hi>Callice</hi> and <hi>Dover,</hi> the other between <hi>Diepe</hi> and <hi>Rye,</hi> for <hi>Popery</hi> to return into <hi>England:</hi> For, when he comes to that part of his <hi>Preface</hi> to Bishop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s <hi>Vindication,</hi> where he considers what likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or how much danger there is of the return of <hi>Popery</hi> into this Nation: <hi>For my own part,</hi> says he, <hi>I know none, but the</hi> Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformist's <hi>boisterous and unreasonable Opposition to the Church of</hi> England. If he think, that the Abrogation of the <hi>Test</hi> may be a means to unite the <hi>Papist,</hi> and the <hi>Dissenter,</hi> which he seems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, by saying, <hi>That the Faction of the</hi> Dissenters <hi>may be made use of, as Instruments (Journey-men Tools) to dissolve and unravel the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish'd Frame of things, and destroy the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and so make an unobstructed Passage for the return of</hi> Popery <hi>in Glory and Triumph;</hi> then he has lest his Cause in the Lurch, and relinquish'd all his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity</hi> at once.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29720:7"/>
            <p> As for the <hi>Papists,</hi> he deals with them after such a rate, that no Man living knows where to have him. In his <hi>Preface</hi> to Bishop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s <hi>Vindication,</hi> he seems neither to Love or Fear 'em: For that, as long as the Church of <hi>England stands in Power and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, it will easily beat back and baffle all the Attemps of</hi> Rome, <hi>and its Adherents; Their plausible Reasons being evidently no more than little Tricks and Sophisms, and seem intended by themselves, rather to abuse the Simple, than satisfie the Wise. Their Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are so undeniable, and the Design of the Church of</hi> England's <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, so apparently</hi> Apostolical, <hi>that those People must needs ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue at a strange and wild rate, that will be demonstrating against Experience, and Ocular Inspection.</hi> So then, the Reformation made by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Points of <hi>Transubstantiation, Worship of Images, Adoration of the Host, and Invocation of Saints,</hi> being <hi>Apostolical;</hi> What must be thought of his <hi>Reasons</hi> against the <hi>Test?</hi> Nay, there is <hi>Nothing could preserve the</hi> Papists <hi>from being hiss'd out of the</hi> Pit, <hi>but that they are extreamly Confident, and most</hi> Readers <hi>sufficiently Ignorant: So that the Church of</hi> England <hi>may safely defy all their Opposition. She does not stand upon such Trembling Foundations, as to be thrust down with Bull-rush</hi> Spears, <hi>and</hi> Oral Traditions, <hi>with</hi> Labyrinths, <hi>and Castles in the</hi> Air.</p>
            <p>But then his Heart misgives him again, and he begins to fear the Return of <hi>Popery</hi> into the Nation, should the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> joyn with the <hi>Papists:</hi> And therefore, at the end of his <hi>Preface,</hi> he begs the <hi>hearty Prayers</hi> of his Friend, <hi>for the Peace and Prosperity of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>for when That is gone,</hi> (farewel Frost) <hi>'twill be hard to find out another, with which any, that are either Honest or Wise, will be over forward to joyn in Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all this, upon better Consideration, as it were in compassion of the despis'd weakness of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Adherents, he undertakes to furnish them with better Arguments of his own, than any they have themselves, to vindicate <hi>Transubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> and clear them from <hi>Idolatry:</hi> For which he strains an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument deduc'd from the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> that cover'd the <hi>Ark.</hi> And yet, in his <hi>Defence</hi> of his <hi>Ecclesiastical Polity,</hi> Pag. 285, 286. he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> together in a Breath; the one for <hi>giving Divine Worship to a lewd Impostor;</hi> the other, to a <hi>Senseless piece of Matter.</hi> And thus, what, by Virtue of <hi>Apparent, Apostolical Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> he call'd (before) a <hi>Senseless piece of Matter,</hi> he has (now) cover'd with the <hi>Cherubim</hi>'s <hi>Golden Wings,</hi> and render'd Adorable by <hi>Scripture</hi> Warrant: But, <hi>Bene scribit, qui bene intelligitur;</hi> what he has Written, he has Written.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29720:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>